<refentry>
   <refmeta>
      <refentrytitle>scalersum</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
   </refmeta>
   <refnamediv>
      <refname>scalersum</refname>
      <refpurpose>Offline scaler summing program</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
      <cmdsynopsis>
         <command>
scalersum <optional><option>--omit-labels</option></optional>
          <optional><option>--name-file</option></optional>
         <optional><option>--flip</option></optional> <replaceable>file1...</replaceable>
         </command>
      </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
             <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
          <para>
            This program computes and output scaler sums from event files. The
            output files can include scaler labels provided from the
            file specified by <option>--name-file</option> or can be without
            labels (if scalers are 32 bits wide, see <literal>NAME FILE FORMAT</literal>
            below).  The orientation of the output can either be one scaler
            per row and one file per column or it can be one scaler per column,
            one row per input file (if <option>--flip</option> is specified).
          </para>
          <para>
            Output files are essentially comma separated fields (CSV)
            and therefore can be easily imported
            to e.g. Excel worksheets.  Note, however that the quoting
            of labels is rather done in a primitive manner and does not support
            embedded quotation marks.  For example a scaler lable like:
            <literal>Detector 1" above beam axis</literal> will get rendered as
            <literal>"Detector 1" above beam axis"</literal> which is incorrect,
            so take care when choosing scaler labels (e.g in the above you might use
            <literal>Detector 1 inch above beam axis</literal> or perhaps even better
            <literal>Detector 2.54cm above beam axis</literal>).
          </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>NAME FILE FORMAT</title>
      <para>
         The <option>--name-file</option> option allows you to supply a file
         containing scaler label information.  The format of this file is not
         the same as the scaler definition file that the scaler display requires.
         See, however <program>makeNameFile</program> (next reference page).
      </para>
      <para>
         The name file format describes each scaler channel, one-per-line.  Each
         line contains four fields that are space separated these contain on order
      </para>
      <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Source ID</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                  The original source id of the scaler channel.  Note that
                  prior to NSCLDAQ-12, the rewrites of the body header performed
                  by <program>glom</program>, lost information about the original
                  source id.  This information is retained in the bodies of
                  NSCLDAQ-12 and later scaler ring items.  This value should
                  refer to this original source id.
               </para>
                <para>
                  Note that when event building is not used, this is normally
                  (though it need not be) zero.
                </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Channel Number</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                  The channel number of the scaler item within its data source.
                  This is the <type>uint32_t</type>
                  offset at which that channel appears in the array
                  of scalers read for that data source.  Offsets are numbered
                  from <literal>0</literal>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Width</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                  Since there are still a few CAMAC systems in use and scalers from
                  those systems are 24 bits wide and may contain bits set in their
                  top 8 bits, this provides the bit-width of the scaler channel.
                  This should normally be either <literal>32</literal>
                  or <literal>24</literal> (CAMAC).  Note, however the software
                  supports any bit width between <literal>1</literal>
                  and <literal>32</literal>.   Wider scalers are not supported
                  in NSCLDAQ as each scaler item in a ring item is 32 bits wide.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Label</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                  The label that identifies the scaler. 
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
         Note that if a scaler label is not provided for a scaler that appears
         in the data, the scaler will be labeled with its sourceid and channel number.
      </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>
<refentry>
   <refmeta>
      <refentrytitle>makeNameFile</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
   </refmeta>
   <refnamediv>
      <refname>makeNameFile</refname>
      <refpurpose>Create name file for scalersum from ScalerDisplay file</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
      <cmdsynopsis>
         <command>
makeNameFile <replaceable>def-file name-file</replaceable>
         </command>
      </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
             <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
          <para>
            See the previous man page (<command>scalersum</command>).
            This utility script reads a scaler display definition
            file (<replaceble>def-file</replaceble>) and writes
            <program>scalersum</program> scaler name file
            (<replaceable>name-file</replaceable>).
          </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>