<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- manpage 3daq -->

<refentry>
   <refmeta>
      <refentrytitle>LIBUSB1 INTRO</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>3daq</manvolnum>
   </refmeta>
   <refnamediv>
      <refname>LIBUSB1 INTRO</refname>
      <refpurpose>Wrappers for userspace USB library.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <synopsis>
#include &lt;USB.h&gt;
#include &lt;USBDeviceInfo.h&gt;
#include &lt;USBDevice.h&gt;
#include &lt;XXUSBUtil.h&gt;

g++ yourstuff -L$DAQLIB -Wl-rpath=$DAQLIB -llibUSB1 `pkg-config libusb-1.0 --libs` `pkg-config libusb-1.0 --cflags`
        </synopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
             <title>
                DESCRIPTION
             </title>
          <para>
            This page provides introductory material that describes the
            <filename>libUSB1</filename> library.  Currently, this provides a
            simplified interface to the libusb-1.0 usb user space library.
            However, by using this class library, rather than libusb-1.0's API
            directly, the maintainers of NSCLDAQ can switch to newer better(?)
            userspace USB libraries with minimal impact on your code.
          </para>
          <para>
            The library defines three classes and a namespace containing
            unbound utilities that are primarily intended to support
            programming the Wiener-JTEC XXUSB controller family.
          </para>
          <para>
            The <classname>USB</classname> provides a top level wrapping
            of operations that don't actually involve a specific device.
            The purpose  of this class is to wrap any library call stream
            context required by the underlying library, and to provide
            an enumeration of the devices on the USB subsystem.
          </para>
          <para>
            Device enumeration comes in the form of <classname>USBDeviceInfo</classname>
            devices.  Each <classname>USBDeviceInfo</classname> object
            provides access to descriptive information about a device attached to
            the USB subsystem that does not require a connection to the device
            itself.  A method is provided, as well to open the device.
          </para>
          <para>
            Open devices are represented by <classname>USBDevice</classname> objects.
            These can be configured and set and transfers of various types
            can be performed to and from the device.
          </para>
          <para>
            The <literal>XXUSBUtil</literal> namespace provides utility functions
            that are intended, primarily, to allow you to manage the Wiener-JTEC
            XXUSB controller family (the VMUSB is a VME usb controller, the
            CCUSB is a CAMAC USB controller).  Support is provided for
            enumerations that are restricted to these devices, downloading lists
            and executing immediate lists.
          </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->