<!-- manpage 1daq -->
<refentry>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>ddasReadout</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>ddasReadout</refname>
        <refpurpose>Run DDASReadout and an associated sorter.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
<command>$DAQBIN/ddasReadout <replaceable>option...</replaceable></command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            As of NSCLDAQ 11.4-000,
            <filename>DDASReadout</filename> has been broken into a pair of
            programs, <filename>DDASReadout</filename> which just reads blocks
            of data from the XIA digitizer modules and <filename>ddasSort</filename>
            which accepts those data and sorts them by timestamp.
            This was done to maximize performance:
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    DDASReadout and ddasSort take advantage of pipeline
                    parallelism to do the sorting in parallel with digitizer
                    readout.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    If necessary the <filename>ddasSort</filename> can be run
                    on a different node than <filename>DDASReadout</filename> making
                    more processing power available.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            A driver, that looks to the ReadoutGUI like an SSHPipe data source
            Allows you to treat this pair of programs as if it were a single
            unified program.
        </para>
        <para>
            The program is called <filename>ddasReadout</filename> (note the
            lower case ddas).  This manpage describes this program.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Options</title>
        <para>
            Note that some program options are mandatory.  Those will be pointed
            out as they are documented.  Note as well that options are prefixed
            with a single <literal>-</literal> rather than a double <literal>-</literal>
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-port</option> <replaceable>integer</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This becomes the <option>--port</option> option on the
                        <filename>DDASReadout</filename> command.  If Tcl server
                         functionality is needed, this is the port on which that
                         server will be listening for connections.  If
                         not specified, this option is not provided to the
                         <filename>DDASReadout</filename> program and that program
                         has its Tcl server functionality disabled.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-readoutring</option> <replaceable>ringname</replaceable> (required)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This option is required.  It specifies the name of the
                        ring buffer into which <filename>DDASReadout</filename>
                        reads data in the host in which that program runs
                        (see <option>-readouthost</option>).
                        This is passed to the <filename>DDASReadout</filename>
                        program as its <option>--ring</option> option
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-cratedir</option> <replaceable>path</replaceable> (required)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Each <filename>DDASReadout</filename> program must run
                        with the current working directory set to a directory that
                        contains its configuration files.  This required option
                        provides that directory.  When <filename>DDASReadout</filename>
                        is run, this will be its working directory.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-sourceid</option> <replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If present this value is relayed to
                        <filename>DDASReadout</filename> as the value of its
                        <option>--sourceid</option> option.  This determines the
                        sourceid used to tag ring items from the readout program.
                        The <filename>ddasSort</filename> program will tag
                        ring items with the same source id as that observed by
                        the ring items it processes.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-init-script</option> <replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If provided this is passed to the <filename>DDASReadout</filename>
                        program as its <option>--init-script</option> the value should
                        be a path to a Tcl script that will be run as the readout program
                        starts.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-log</option> <replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If provided, the value of this option will be passed
                        to <filename>DDASREADOUT</filename> as its
                        <option>--log</option> option.  This specifies the path
                        into which the readout program logs intersting information.
                        If the file does not exist it is created.  The path
                        prefix must be a directory that's writable by the
                        user.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-debug</option> <replaceable>log-level</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If provided, passes the debug level to the
                        <filename>DDASReadout</filename> program. This is an integer
                        in the range 0-2 inclusive and determines the sort of
                        information written to the log file.   The higher the number,
                        the more verbose the logging.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-readouthost</option> <replaceable>dns-name</replaceable> (required)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Determines which system the <filename>DDASReadout</filename>
                        program will be run in.  This must be a system that is
                        connected to a DDAS crate and has its PLX drivers
                        loaded.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-sortring</option> <replaceable>ringname</replaceable> (required)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Provides the name of the ring into which
                        <filename>ddasSort</filename> puts the sorted hit ring items.
                        If the ringbuffer does no yet exist, it will be created.
                        This is a ring name not a URI.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-sorthost</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable> (required)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Provides the DNS name of the host in which the
                        <filename>ddasSort</filename> will be run.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-window</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Describes ow old events must be before they are emitted
                        (in seconds).  The <filename>ddasSort</filename> program
                        emits data from a sliding window.  This parameter
                        defaults to 10 seconds.  If you change this value be sure to
                        ensure the event builder sees no data late or out of order
                        fragments from this data source.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Using the <filename>ddasReadout</filename> driver</title>
        <para>
            <filename>ddasReadout</filename> is intended to be used as a
            data source in the <filename>ReadoutShell</filename> GUI.
            It does not actually matter much where the <filename>ddasReadout</filename>
            program is run as it will be running the actual readout and sort
            programs where you tell it to using its command line options.
        </para>
        <para>
            Use the <guimenu>Data Source</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add..</guimenuitem>
            menu to specify the data source.   <filename>ddasReadout</filename>
            is intended to be used as an <literal>SSHPipe</literal> data source.
            It will relay commands sent to it to the actual readout program.
            it will relay output and error messages to the its own stdout
            which is captured by the SSHPipe driver and relayed to a tab
            for the data source on the ReadoutShell's GUI.
        </para>
        <para>
            When setting up the event builder be sure to point the data source
            at the <filename>ddasSort</filename> output ring.  That's where
            the individual time-stamped hits will be placed.  The
            <filename>DDDASReadout</filename> ring will get ring items
            that consist of blocks of unsorted hits.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->